Ruhl Jacob Bartlett Papers MS042
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Ruhl Jacob Bartlett Papers
1936 -- 1984
1923 -- 1993
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Bartlett, Ruhl Jacob
MS042
2.4 Linear Feet
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes biographical information, news clippings, correspondence, diplomas and distinctions, photos, publications, speeches, and a congressional testimony transcript related to Bartlett's research, publishing, and public and academic service.
Biographical / Historical
Born on January 24 1897 in Webster, West Virginia, Ruhl Jacob Bartlett was a professor and scholar of American and diplomatic history. He attended public schools in Webster, West Virginia, and Jackson Center, Ohio, and served in the United States Navy during and after World War I serving as a Navy seaman in training at Ohio State University and at the Great Lakes stations from 1918-1919. He holds an A. B. from Ohio University (1920), an M. A. from the University of Cincinnati (1923), and a PhD from Ohio State University (1927). He taught at Ohio high-schools from 1920-1923 and as instructor in history at the University of Iowa (1925-26).
He taught at Tufts for over 40 years from 1927 to 1972. Bartlett began as an Assistant Professor of History at Tufts in 1927. He then served as: Dickson Professor of English and American History, 1932-68; Chair, Department of History, 1934-56; Interim Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, 1938-39; Acting Dean, Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, 1943-44; Professor of Diplomatic History, Fletcher School, 1942-68 (concurrent with appointments in the Department of History). In 1968, Bartlett was voted emeritus status in both the Fletcher School and the College of Arts and Sciences, and he retired in the summer 1972. He received an honorary degree of Doctor of Laws from Tufts in 1975. The Ruhl Jacob Bartlett scholarship at the Fletcher School was established in his honor.
Bartlett published several books, numerous articles and book reviews on topics such as American foreign relations and foreign policy, Latin American politics, and the League to Enforce Peace. In 1967, he testified before the U.S. Senate's Committee on Foreign Affairs and House Subcommittee Committee on International Security and Scientific Affairs of the committee on International Relations on the balance of decision making power in the U.S. Government.
Bartlett married Lela M. Work in 1924; they had no children. After her death he married Cathleen L. Gorrie in 1972. Bartlett died in California on September 29, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Bartlett, Ruhl Jacob, 1897-1995; Faculty papers
- Ruhl J. Bartlett Papers, 1923 -- 1993; MS042.001; 2.4 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains scholarly material created by Bartlett including publications, speeches, and a congressional testimony transcript. It contains personal and professional letters, biographical material (such as diplomas and distinctions), photographs, and newspaper clippings.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Articles, 1941 -- 1978; MS042.001.001.00001 (Box Shared 133)
  - Book reviews, 1940 -- 1980; MS042.001.001.00002 (Box Shared 133)
  - Correspondence, 1939 -- 1993; MS042.001.001.00003 (Box Shared 133)
  - High School Life Certificate and Doctoral diploma, 1923 -- 1927; MS042.001.001.00004 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 6)
  - Honorary doctorate and Emeritus scroll, 1968 -- 1975; MS042.001.001.00005 (Box Shared 133)
  - Letters/miscellaneous, 1939 -- 1982; MS042.001.001.00006 (Box Shared 133)
    Contains letters autographed by Herbert Hoover, Walter Lippmann, and Justice Charles Evans Hughes
  - Newspaper clippings, 1964 -- 1973; MS042.001.001.00007 (Box Shared 133)
  - Personal/biographical, 1936 -- 1975; MS042.001.001.00008 (Box Shared 133)
    Includes a speech made by Daniel P. Moynihan from May 25, 1975 honoring Prof. Bartlett; Moynihan had been one of his students at the Fletcher School.
  - Speeches, 1940 -- 1975; MS042.001.001.00009 (Box Shared 133)
  - Speeches and Articles, 1923 -- 1966; MS042.001.001.00010 (Box Shared 133)
  - Testimony, U.S. Congress, 1967 -- 1969; MS042.001.001.00011 (Box Shared 133)
  - Vita and Bibliography, 1984; MS042.001.001.00012 (Box Shared 133)
  - Commemorative album of letters, 1968; MS042.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
    RJB received this album of letters in June 1968 on the occasion of a dinner given in his honor by Fletcher Alumni. Contrary to general perception, this dinner was not for his retirement because he did not retire until 1972. RJB comments on this in one of his letters to Russell Miller.